# Kaiyang Zhou

Research Fellow School of Computer Science and Engineering Nanyang Technological University, Singapore

E-mail: kaiyang.zhou@ntu.edu.sg | Homepage | Google Scholar | Github

### **Research Interests**

Representation learning, foundation models, domain adaptation, domain generalization, semi-supervised learning, unsupervised learning, out-of-distribution detection, generative modeling, reinforcement learning, low-power design, and explainable AI

Areas: Machine Learning & Computer Vision

## **Research Highlights**

My research revolves around the development of *generalizable* (across changing data distributions) and *efficient* (small / fast / low-power) machine learning models—particularly those based on neural networks—for large-scale data analytics in an open world, with applications to computer vision and others. I have published more than 20 papers at major journals and conferences in relevant fields, such as TPAMI (flagship journal in AI with IF=24.31), IJCV (flagship journal in computer vision with IF=13.37), and the three prominent computer vision conferences (i.e., CVPR, ICCV and ECCV).

Google Scholar Citations: 3,000 citations with h-index 15 (as of Mar 2023).

## **Appointments**

Nanyang Technological University, Singapore Research Fellow with Prof. Ziwei Liu and Prof. Chen Change Loy	2021.01 – present
Samsung AI Center Cambridge, UK Research Intern with Prof. Tao Xiang	2018.11 – 2019.05
SIAT-MMLAB, Chinese Academy of Sciences, China Research Assistant with Prof. Yu Qiao	2016.10 – 2017.08
ducation	

## **Education**

PhD in Computer Science University of Surrey, UK Supervised by Prof. Tao Xiang	2020
MSc in Advanced Computing (Distinction) University of Bristol, UK Supervised by Prof. Majid Mirmehdi and Dr. Adeline Paiement	2016
BSc in Computer Science (First Class Honor) University of Ulster, UK	2015

#### **Publications**

#### **Journal impact factors**:

IEEE Transactions on Pattern Analysis and Machine Intelligence (TPAMI): 24.31 International Journal of Computer Vision (IJCV): 13.37 IEEE Transactions on Image Processing (TIP): 11.04

#### Refereed journal articles:

- 1. Yuhang Zang, <u>Kaiyang Zhou</u>, Chen Huang, and Chen Change Loy. Semi-supervised and long-tailed object detection with cascadematch. *International Journal of Computer Vision (IJCV)*, 2023.
- 2. <u>Kaiyang Zhou</u>, Ziwei Liu, Yu Qiao, Tao Xiang, and Chen Change Loy. Domain generalization: A survey. *IEEE Transactions on Pattern Analysis and Machine Intelligence (TPAMI)*, 2022.
- 3. <u>Kaiyang Zhou</u>, Jingkang Yang, Chen Change Loy, and Ziwei Liu. Learning to prompt for vision-language models. *International Journal of Computer Vision (IJCV)*, 130:2337–2348, 2022.
- 4. Zhongying Deng, <u>Kaiyang Zhou</u>, Da Li, Junjun He, Yi-Zhe Song, and Tao Xiang. Dynamic instance domain adaptation. *IEEE Transactions on Image Processing (TIP)*, 31:4585–4597, 2022.
- 5. <u>Kaiyang Zhou</u>, Yongxin Yang, Yu Qiao, and Tao Xiang. Domain adaptive ensemble learning. *IEEE Transactions on Image Processing (TIP)*, 30:8008–8018, 2021.
- 6. <u>Kaiyang Zhou</u>, Yongxin Yang, Andrea Cavallaro, and Tao Xiang. Learning generalisable omni-scale representations for person re-identification. *IEEE Transactions on Pattern Analysis and Machine Intelligence (TPAMI)*, 2021.

#### **Refereed conference papers:**

- 1. Tingwei Wang, Da Li, <u>Kaiyang Zhou</u>, Tao Xiang, and Yi-Zhe Song. Learning to augment via implicit differentiation for domain generalization. In *British Machine Vision Conference (BMVC)*, 2022. **Oral**.
- Jingkang Yang, Pengyun Wang, Dejian Zou, Zitang Zhou, Kunyuan Ding, Wenxuan Peng, Haoqi Wang, Guangyao Chen, Bo Li, Yiyou Sun, Xuefeng Du, <u>Kaiyang Zhou</u>, Wayne Zhang, Dan Hendrycks, Yixuan Li, and Ziwei Liu. Openood: Benchmarking generalized out-of-distribution detection. In *Proceedings* of the Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS) Track on Datasets and Benchmarks, 2022.
- 3. Jingkang Yang, Yi Zhe Ang, Zujin Guo, <u>Kaiyang Zhou</u>, Wayne Zhang, and Ziwei Liu. Panoptic scene graph generation. In *European conference on computer vision (ECCV)*. Springer, 2022.
- 4. Yuhang Zang, Wei Li, <u>Kaiyang Zhou</u>, Chen Huang, and Chen Change Loy. Open-vocabulary detr with conditional matching. In *European conference on computer vision (ECCV)*. Springer, 2022. **Oral**, 158/5,803=2.7%.
- 5. <u>Kaiyang Zhou</u>, Jingkang Yang, Chen Change Loy, and Ziwei Liu. Conditional prompt learning for vision-language models. In *Proceedings of the IEEE/CVF Conference on Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition (CVPR)*, pages 16816–16825, 2022. **Among top-100 most cited papers in 2022 (42th)**, **provided by Zeta Alpha (link)**.
- 6. Zhongying Deng, <u>Kaiyang Zhou</u>, Yongxin Yang, and Tao Xiang. Domain attention consistency for multi-source domain adaptation. In *British Machine Vision Conference (BMVC)*, 2021.
- 7. Yezhen Wang, Bo Li, Tong Che, <u>Kaiyang Zhou</u>, Ziwei Liu, and Dongsheng Li. Energy-based openworld uncertainty modeling for confidence calibration. In *Proceedings of the IEEE/CVF International Conference on Computer Vision (ICCV)*, pages 9302–9311, 2021.
- 8. <u>Kaiyang Zhou</u>, Yongxin Yang, Yu Qiao, and Tao Xiang. Domain generalization with mixstyle. In *International Conference on Learning Representations (ICLR)*, 2021.
- 9. <u>Kaiyang Zhou</u>, Yongxin Yang, Timothy Hospedales, and Tao Xiang. Learning to generate novel domains for domain generalization. In *European conference on computer vision (ECCV)*, volume 12361, pages 561–578. Springer, 2020.
- 10. <u>Kaiyang Zhou</u>, Yongxin Yang, Timothy Hospedales, and Tao Xiang. Deep domain-adversarial image generation for domain generalisation. In *Proceedings of the AAAI Conference on Artificial Intelligence (AAAI)*, volume 34, pages 13025–13032, 2020.
- 11. <u>Kaiyang Zhou</u>, Yongxin Yang, Andrea Cavallaro, and Tao Xiang. Omni-scale feature learning for person re-identification. In *Proceedings of the IEEE/CVF International Conference on Computer Vision (ICCV)*, pages 3702–3712, 2019.
- 12. <u>Kaiyang Zhou</u>, Tao Xiang, and Andrea Cavallaro. Video summarisation by classification with deep reinforcement learning. In *British Machine Vision Conference (BMVC)*, 2018. **Oral**, 37/862=4.3%.

- 13. <u>Kaiyang Zhou</u>, Yu Qiao, and Tao Xiang. Deep reinforcement learning for unsupervised video summarization with diversity-representativeness reward. In *Proceedings of the AAAI Conference on Artificial Intelligence (AAAI)*, volume 32, 2018. **Oral, 418/3,800=11%**.
- 14. <u>Kaiyang Zhou</u>, Adeline Paiement, and Majid Mirmehdi. Detecting humans in rgb-d data with cnns. In 2017 Fifteenth IAPR International Conference on Machine Vision Applications (MVA), pages 306–309. IEEE, 2017.

#### Workshop papers and technical reports:

- 1. <u>Kaiyang Zhou</u>, Chen Change Loy, and Ziwei Liu. Semi-supervised domain generalization with stochastic stylematch. In *NeurIPS 2021 Workshop on Distribution Shifts: Connecting Methods and Applications*, 2021.
- 2. <u>Kaiyang Zhou</u> and Tao Xiang. Torchreid: A library for deep learning person re-identification in pytorch. *arXiv preprint arXiv:1910.10093*, 2019.

#### Theses:

- 1. Kaiyang Zhou. *Adaptation and Generalization Across Domains in Visual Recognition with Deep Neural Networks*. PhD thesis, University of Surrey, 2020. pdf
- 2. Kaiyang Zhou. *Human Detection with Convolutional Neural Networks in RGB-D Images*. MSc thesis, University of Bristol, 2016. (Best Master's Thesis.)
- 3. Kaiyang Zhou. *Computer Vision-based Local Navigation for Mobile Robots*. BSc thesis, Ulster University, 2015.

#### **Patents**

- 1. "Dynamic prompt generation technology for vision-language models," filed through NTU & Sense-Time, Singapore Patent No. 10202202104P, 2022; China Patent No. 202210431968.4, 2022.
- 2. "Deep learning-based video summarization method, device and end equipment," filed through SIAT, China Patent No. CN201711374076.0, 2018.

### **Grants**

**Co-I**, "3D Geometry and Semantic Modeling for Human-Scene Interaction," MOE AcRF Tier 2. (S\$ 613,574.00.)

### **Professional Services**

#### **Guest Editor** IJCV Special Issue on The Promises and Dangers of Large Vision Models (lead guest editor) 2023 **Area Chair / Senior Program Committee** AAAI Conference on Artificial Intelligence (AAAI) 2023 British Machine Vision Conference (BMVC) 2022 **Organizer** CVPR 2023 Tutorial: Prompting in Vision<sup>†</sup> 2023 ICLR 2023 Workshop: What do we need for successful domain generalization? 2023 ECCV 2022 Computer Vision in the Wild Challenges 2022 2022 The AI Talks<sup>†</sup> †: Lead organizer

### Reviewer

IEEE Transactions on Pattern Analysis and Machine Intelligence (TPAMI)

IEEE Transactions on Image Processing (TIP)

IEEE Transactions on Multimedia (TMM)

IEEE Transactions on Circuits and Systems for Video Technology (TCSVT)

International Journal of Computer Vision (IJCV)

ACM Transactions on Multimedia Computing, Communications, and Applications (TOMM)

International Conference on Learning Representations (ICLR)

Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS)

International Conference on Machine Learning (ICML)

AAAI Conference on Artificial Intelligence (AAAI)

IEEE Conference on Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition (CVPR)

International Conference on Computer Vision (ICCV)

European Conference on Computer Vision (ECCV)

British Machine Vision Conference (BMVC)

## **Teaching**

Lecturer / Guest Lecturer, Nanyang Technological University Open-World Visual Recognition (AI6126: Advanced Computer Vision) Object Detection (OpenMMLab Workshop)	Apr 2022, Mar 2023 Jun 2021
<b>Teaching Assistant</b> , Queen Mary University of London ECS797: Machine Learning for Visual Data Analytics ECS708: Machine Learning	Spring 2018 Fall 2017, Fall 2018

## **Mentoring**

Xinyu Pan (PhD at CUHK)	2022 – present
Yuanhan Zhang (PhD at NTU)	2022 – present
Yuhang Zang (PhD at NTU)	2021 – present
Jingkang Yang (PhD at NTU)	2021 – present
Zhongying Deng (PhD at Surrey)	2019 - 2020

### **Talks**

CVPR 2023 Tutorial on Prompting in Vision Prompt learning for visual recognition and generation	Jun 2023
<b>Hong Kong Baptist University</b> , CS Department Open-world visual computing with foundation models: A prompt learning perspective	Mar 2023
Nanyang Technological University, School of CSE Towards generalizable and efficient learning system designs	Feb 2023
National University of Singapore, ECE Department Towards generalizable and efficient learning system designs	Jan 2023
Nanyang Technological University, IET CV Workshop Visual recognition: From closed-set discrete labels to open-set natural language supervision	Oct 2021
University of Surrey, Centre for Vision, Speech and Signal Processing (CVSSP)  Adaptation and generalization across domains in visual recognition with deep neural networks	Sep 2020
Nanyang Technological University, MMLab Multi-source domain generalization and adaptation	Jul 2020
Queen Mary University of London, Intelligent Sensing Summer School Summarizing videos with deep reinforcement learning	Aug 2018

### **Honors & Awards**

Outstanding Reviewer, <u>ECCV 2022</u>	2022
Outstanding Reviewer, <u>ICCV 2021</u>	2021
Top 25% of Program Committee Members, <u>AAAI 2021</u>	2021
University Strategic Funds Studentship, University of Surrey	2019
Queen Mary Principal's Research Studentship, Queen Mary University of London	2017
Innovation Scholarship (for contribution to patent), SIAT Chinese Academy of Sciences	2017
Best Master's Thesis, University of Bristol CS Department	2016

## **Selected Open-Source Software**

I promote open-source AI research and have been an activate contributor to the open-source community on Github. I have developed several open-source projects widely used by both academia and industry (with over 6k stars received in total on Github). Below are the two most representative projects. See my <u>Github page</u> for more.

#### 1. Torchreid

- a well-documented Python library for research on deep learning-based person re-identification
- provides a model zoo containing various pre-trained models
- receives 3.7k+ stars on Github (ranked No. 1 by popularity on Github for person re-id)
- link: github.com/KaiyangZhou/deep-person-reid

### 2. Dassl.pytorch

- a Python library for research on domain generalization and domain adaptation
- receives 700+ stars on Github
- link: github.com/KaiyangZhou/Dassl.pytorch

Last update: March 2023